[Music]
time magazine famously exhorted people
to eat butter no doubt selling lots of
magazines but perhaps
selling the public short they followed
up with an article doubling down saying
that the case for eating butter just got
stronger
based on this study a systematic review
and meta-analysis of butter consumption
pooling all the studies each daily
serving of butter was associated with
only a one percent higher risk of death
wait this is the study making the case
stronger to eat butter
further the study suggests that swapping
like a spoonful of oil in place of
butter every day would drop the risk of
diabetes eight percent
thus even with an absence of major
health associations in the present
investigation healthier alternatives may
be available
but a one percent increase in risk is
pretty tiny why didn't they find a
larger effect
well i mean it is just a tiny part of
people's overall diets
it's illustrative to review
the candy literature the national
confectioners association is fond of
contracting with scientists for hire
like exponent incorporated infamous for
shilling for big tobacco and chemical
companies
encouraging people to eat candy every
day in moderation you know like 15 to 25
jelly beans a day
parents who restrict foods in an attempt
to moderate a child's intake of calories
are just gonna make their kids fat
see parents use coercive practices to
limit children's access to palatable
energy dense or low nutrient foods
parents have the gall to tell their kids
when how often or how much candy can be
consumed
don't they know butter butterscotch is
back
see evidence suggests that candy is not
associated with adverse health effects
don't believe me here you go ten
thousand kids surveyed asked if they'd
eaten candy within the last 24 hours
compared to those who said no
and they conclude that candy consumption
was not associated with adverse health
parameters in children or adolescents
and this a study in which authors
declared no conflicts of interest
i mean yeah it was a study about candy
funded by the candy industry but
no conflicts of interest here
do you see how with such a blunt
instrument it would be hard to tease out
the specific health effects of candy but
look we don't need a study
since we already know what candy is it's
candy it's mostly pure sugar we already
eat too much sugar we don't need more
you don't need to pay off researchers to
come up with a study like this or
this
we already know what butter is
it's butter it's mostly pure saturated
fat we already eat too much saturated
fat we don't need more
anyway
it gets even crazier candy consumers
were less likely to be overweight and
obese than non-candy consumers so hey
maybe the candy company was right
past the peeps
is candy eating really a way to control
body weight
who can name me an alternative
explanation of why obese children eat
less candy
right reverse causation perhaps it's not
cutting down on candy that led to
obesity but rather obesity leading to
cutting down on candy in other words the
reported candy consumption reflects the
consequences of obesity not the cause
just like people with heart disease may
cut down on butter right clouding the
association
and remember it was reported candy
consumption which brings up the specter
of reporting bias
in other words overweight kids make
guiltily under-report their intake of
candy to a greater extent than do those
of normal weight
i mean otherwise what would the
implications of such a finding be do we
want to randomize kids to eat more candy
to see if it makes them lose weight
it's doubtful that any ethical committee
would be happy about that kind of
proposal
but you don't know until you put it to
the test feed folks extra candy or
peanuts the same number of extra
calories and surprise surprise those
that ate all that extra candy gained
more weight
but what about that
interventional trial showing that candy
can improve adhd symptoms
if you're the mars candy bar company and
you want to fund a study showing candy
bars help kids focus
what would you do
the parents were sent a formal letter
instructing them to send their kids to
school hungry without breakfast and then
gave them a candy bar
or
basically nothing an aspartame beverage
and what do you know feeding kids
something rather than nothing enhance
their ability to stay on task
that reminds me of the famous frosted
mini wheats ad clinically shown to
improve kids attentiveness by nearly 20
with a really fine print explaining that
this was compared to kids that ate
nothing at all
butter has been put to the test too give
people a single meal with butter and you
get a boost of inflammatory gene
expression within just hours of
consumption significantly more than the
same amount of fat in olive oil or
particularly walnut form
you can randomize people to foods made
with all sorts of different fats and
butter was shown to be the worst in
terms of ldl cholesterol
yeah but these were short-term studies
it's not like you can randomize people
to eat or avoid butter for years unless
they're locked up in a mental hospital
whereby switching diets you can raise or
lower their cholesterol and cut coronary
vents by about 40 percent
though they also cut down on meat and
eggs so it wasn't just butter
yeah but it's not like you can get a
whole country to cut down on butter oh
but you can a 75 drop in butter
consumption in finland helped create an
80 drop in heart disease mortality
which was driven largely by the
country-wide drop in cholesterol levels
which was largely driven by the
country-wide dietary changes to lower
saturated fat intake like the move away
from butter
the bottom line is that researchers have
put it to the test randomized controlled
trials involving more than 50 000 people
and the more you decrease saturated fat
content the more your cholesterol drops
the greater the protection
lifestyle advice to all those at risk
for cardiovascular diseases to lower the
risk of our number one killer of men and
women population groups should continue
to be advised to permanently reduce
their saturated fat intake
the american heart association got so
fed up with industry attempts to confuse
people they released a presidential
advisory in 2017 to make it as clear as
they could the main sources of saturated
fat to be decreased include
butter
[Music]
uh